Franzen, Cola mss., 1982-2010 LMC 2615
Lilly Library
Franzen, Cola mss.
1982-2010
Lilly Library
Franzen, Cola.
LMC 2615
7 Boxes
The Franzen, Cola mss., 1982-2010, consist of manuscripts, drafts, correspondence and other material relating to literary translations from the Spanish by translator Cola Franzen, 1923-2018.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Born in Hart County, Georgia, Franzen (née Wakefield) has published over twenty books of literary translations from the Spanish. She primarily translates the work of contemporary Latin American poets, including Saul Yurkievich (Argentina), Antonio José Ponte (Cuba) and Juan Cameron (Chile), as well as Spanish poets like Jorge Guillén and Frederico García Lorca. She has also translated work on photography and art.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Translations; III. Presentations; IV. Critiques; V. Clippings; VI. Publications; VII. Audio-Visual Materials; VIII. Realia.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondents include: Aurora Bernárdez; Catherine Mayo; Guillermo Núñez; Nancy Peters; Reina María Rodriguez; Robert Wechsler; Rachel Weiss; Saul Yurkievich.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2006-2010
Translators --Biography.; Literature--translating; Franzen, Cola --Correspondence.
- I. Correspondence (Box 1)
  - A (Box 1)
  - Ba-Bi (Box 1)
  - Bernárdez, Aurora (Box 1)
  - Bl-Bu (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - D-E (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - G (Box 1)
  - H (Box 1)
  - Harvard University Press, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Hardvard University Press, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - I-K (Box 1)
  - L (Box 1)
  - Mah-May (Box 1)
  - Mayo, Catherine (Box 1)
  - Mc-Mu (Box 1)
  - Núñez, Guillermo, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Núñez, Guillermo, 1987-2010; undated (Box 1)
  - O-Q (Box 1)
  - Peters, Nancy (Box 1)
  - R (Box 1)
  - Rodriguez, Reina María (Box 1)
  - S-T (Box 1)
  - U-V (Box 1)
  - W (Box 1)
  - Wechsler, Robert (Box 1)
  - Weiss, Rachel (Box 2)
  - Yurkievich, Saul, 1982-2005; (24 folders) (Box 2)
  - Z (Box 2)
  - Unknown (Box 2)
- II. Translations. (Box 3)
  - Alvarez Bravo, Manuel (Box 3)
  - Aresti, Carlos (Box 3)
  - Cameron, Juan (Box 3)
  - Casado, Alberto (Box 3)
  - Cortázar, Julio (Box 3)
  - Estorino, Abelardo (Box 3)
  - Grandmothers of the Plaza de Mayo (Box 3)
  - García Lorca, Frederico (Box 3)
  - Guillén, Jorge (Box 3)
  - Hernández, Orlando (Box 3)
  - Huidobro, Vincente (Box 3)
  - Iturbide, Graciela (Box 3)
  - Jiménez, Ariel (Box 3)
  - Del Llano, Eduardo (Box 3)
  - Manjarrez Cuéllar, Graciela (Box 3)
  - Marco, Tomás (Box 3)
  - Medina, Cuauhtémac (Box 3)
  - Molina, Juan Antonio (Box 3)
  - Moréjon, Nancy (Box 3)
  - Mosquero, Geraldo Africa in the Art of Latin America (Box 3)
  - Mosquero, Geraldo Art and Religion in Elso (Box 3)
  - Mosquero, Geraldo Fresh Cream (Box 3)
  - Mosquero, Geraldo New Cuban Art (Box 3)
  - Núnez, Guillermo (Box 3)
  - Notes (Box 3)
  - Pérez-Oramas, Luis Enrique (Box 3)
  - Ponte, Antonio José (Box 4)
  - Puebla, Javier (Box 4)
  - Rodriquez, Eduardo Luis (Box 4)
  - Valdés Figueroa, Eugenio (Box 4)
  - Various Authors Art Cuba (Box 4)
  - Various Authors Art Nexus (Box 4)
  - Various Authors, Artists' Statements (Box 4)
  - Various Authors, Cisneros Foundation (Box 4)
  - Wellesley College (Box 4)
  - Yurkievich, Saul Confluencia (Box 4)
  - Yurkievich, Saul Background Noise, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Yurkievich, Saul In the Image and the Likeness (Box 4)
  - Yurkievich, Saul Late He Knew It (Box 4)
  - Yurkievich, Saul, Various (Box 4)
  - Zóbel, Fernando (Box 4)
  - Zaid, Gabriel (Box 4)
- III. Presentations. (Box 4)
  - List of Readings (Box 4)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - 1986 (Box 4)
  - 1987 (Box 4)
  - 1988 (Box 4)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - 1991 (Box 4)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - 1994 (Box 4)
  - 1995 (Box 5)
  - 1996 (Box 5)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - 1999 (Box 5)
  - 2000 (Box 5)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 5)
  - 2003 (Box 5)
  - 2004 (Box 5)
  - 2005-2006 (Box 5)
  - 2007-2008, undated (Box 5)
- IV. Critiques. (Box 5)
  - Reviews (Box 5)
  - Readers' Reports (Box 5)
- V. Clippings. (Box 5)
  - Academy of American Poets (Box 5)
  - Chipasula, Frank (Box 5)
  - General (Box 5)
  - Newsletters (Box 5)
- VI. Publications. (Box 5)
  - A (Box 5)
  - Aperture (Box 5)
  - C-D (Box 5)
  - Graham House Review (Box 5)
  - Grand Street, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Harvard Review (Box 6)
  - M-N (Box 6)
  - New Orleans Review (Box 6)
  - O.ARS, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - P-R (Box 6)
  - Rethinking Marxism (Box 6)
  - S-T (Box 6)
- VII. Audio-Visual Materials. (Box 6)
  - Yurkievich, Saul Poems, (1 tape) (Box 6)
- VIII. Realia. (Box 6)
  - Huidobro Presentation Sweatshirt (Box 6)